one conversation at a time. And the question is, who do you want to remember -- if you had just 45 minutes with your grandmother? What's interesting, in conversations with the founder, Dave Isay, we always actually talked about this as a little bit of a subversive project, because when you think about it, it's actually not really about the stories that are being told, it's about listening, and it's about the questions that you get to ask, questions that you may not have permission to on any other day. I'm going to play you just a couple of quick excerpts from the project. [Jesus Melendez talking about poet Pedro Pietri's final moments] Jesus Melendez: We took off, and as we were ascending, before we had leveled off, our level-off point was 45,000 feet, so before we had leveled off, Pedro began leaving us, and the beauty about it is that I believe that there's something after life. You can see it in Pedro. [Danny Perasa to his wife Annie Perasa married 26 years] Danny Perasa: See, the thing of it is, I always feel guilty when I say "I love you" to you, and I say it so often. I say it to remind you that as dumpy as I am, it's coming from me, it's like hearing a beautiful song from a busted old radio, and it's nice of you to keep the radio around the house. (Laughter) [Michael Wolmetz with his girlfriend Debora Brakarz] Michael Wolmetz: So this is the ring that my father gave to my mother, and we can leave it there. And he saved up and he purchased this, and he proposed to my mother with this, and so I thought that I would give it to you so that he could be with us for this also. So I'm going to share a mic with you right now, Debora. Where's the right finger? Debora Brakarz: (Crying) MW: Debora, will you please marry me? DB: Yes. Of course. I love you. (Kissing) MW: So kids, this is how your mother and I got married, in a booth in Grand Central Station with my father's ring. My grandfather was a cab driver for 40 years. He used to pick people up here every day. So it seems right. Jake Barton: So I have to say I did not actually choose those individual samples to make you cry because they all make you cry. The entire project is predicated on this act of love which is listening itself. And that motion of building an institution out of a moment of conversation and listening is actually a lot of what my firm, Local Projects, is doing with our engagements in general. So we're a media design firm, and we're working with a broad array of different institutions building media installations for museums and public spaces. Our latest engagement is the Cleveland Museum of Art, which we've created an engagement called Gallery One for. And Gallery One is an interesting project because it started with this massive, $350 million expansion for the Cleveland Museum of Art, and we actually brought in this piece specifically to grow new capacity, new audiences, at the same time that the museum itself is growing. Glenn Lowry, the head of MoMA, put it best when he said, "We want visitors to actually cease being visitors. Visitors are transient. We want people who live here, people who have ownership." And so what we're doing is making a broad array of different ways for people to actually engage with the material inside of these galleries, so you can still have a traditional gallery experience, but if you're interested, you can actually engage with any individual artwork and see the original context from where it's from, or manipulate the work itself. So, for example, you can click on this individual lion head, and this is where it originated from, 1300 B.C. Or this individual piece here, you can see the actual bedroom. It really changes the way you think about this type of a tempera painting. This is one of my favorites because you see the studio itself. This is Rodin's bust. You get the sense of this incredible factory for creativity. And it makes you think about literally the hundreds or thousands of years of human creativity and how each individual artwork stands in for part of that story. This is Picasso, of course embodying so much of it from the 20th century. And so our next interface, which I'll show you, actually leverages that idea of this lineage of creativity. It's an algorithm that actually allows you to browse the actual museum's collection using facial recognition. So this person's making different faces, and it's actually drawing forth different objects from the collection that connect with exactly how she's looking. And so you can imagine that, as people are performing inside of the museum itself, you get this sense of this emotional connection, this way in which our face connects with the thousands and tens of thousands of years. This is an interface that actually allows you to draw and then draws forth objects using those same shapes. So more and more we're trying to find ways for people to actually author things inside of the museums themselves, to be creative even as they're looking at other people's creativity and understanding them. So in this wall, the collections wall, you can actually see all 3,000 artworks all at the same time, and you can actually author your own individual walking tours of the museum, so you can share them, and someone can take a tour with the museum director or a tour with their little cousin. But all the while that we've been working on this engagement for Cleveland, we've also been working in the background on really our largest engagement to date, and that's the 9/11 Memorial and Museum. So we started in 2006 as part of a team with Thinc Design to create the original master plan for the museum, and then we've done all the media design both for the museum and the memorial and then the media production. So the memorial opened in 2011, and the museum's going to open next year in 2014. And you can see from these images, the site is so raw and almost archaeological. And of course the event itself is so recent, somewhere between history and current events, it was a huge challenge to imagine how do you actually live up to a space like this, an event like this, to actually tell that story. And so what we started with was really a new way of thinking about building an institution, through a project called Make History, which we launched in 2009. So it's estimated that a third of the world watched 9/11 live, and a third of the world heard about it within 24 hours, making it really by nature of when it happened, this unprecedented moment of global awareness. And so we launched this to capture the stories from all around the world, through video, through photos, through written history, and so people's experiences on that day, which was, in fact, this huge risk for the institution to make its first move this open platform. But that was coupled together with this oral histories booth, really the simplest we've ever made, where you locate yourself on a map. It's in six languages, and you can tell your own story about what happened to you on that day. And when we started seeing the incredible images and stories that came forth from all around the world -- this is obviously part of the landing gear -- we really started to understand that there was this amazing symmetry between the event itself, between the way that people were telling the stories of the event, and how we ourselves needed to tell that story. This image in particular really captured our attention at the time, because it so much sums up that event. This is a shot from the Brooklyn-Battery Tunnel. There's a firefighter that's stuck, actually, in traffic, and so the firefighters themselves are running a mile and a half to the site itself with upwards of 70 pounds of gear on their back. And we got this amazing email that said, "While viewing the thousands of photos on the site, I unexpectedly found a photo of my son. It was a shock emotionally, yet a blessing to find this photo," and he was writing because he said, "I'd like to personally thank the photographer for posting the photo, as it meant more than words can describe to me to have access to what is probably the last photo ever taken of my son." And it really made us recognize what this institution needed to be in order to actually tell that story. We can't have just a historian or a curator narrating objectively in the third person about an event like that, when you have the witnesses to history who are going to make their way through the actual museum itself. And so we started imagining the museum, along with the creative team at the museum and the curators, thinking about how the first voice that you would hear inside the museum would actually be of other visitors. And so we created this idea of an opening gallery called We Remember. And I'll just play you part of a mockup of it, but you get a sense of what it's like to actually enter into that moment in time and be transported back in history. (Video) Voice 1: I was in Honolulu, Hawaii. Voice 2: I was in Cairo, Egypt. Voice 3: Sur les Champs-Élysées, à Paris. Voice 4: In college, at U.C. Berkeley. Voice 5: I was in Times Square. Voice 6: São Paolo, Brazil. (Multiple voices) Voice 7: It was probably about 11 o'clock at night. Voice 8: I was driving to work at 5:45 local time in the morning. Voice 9: We were actually in a meeting when someone barged in and said, "Oh my God, a plane has just crashed into the World Trade Center." Voice 10: Trying to frantically get to a radio. Voice 11: When I heard it over the radio -- Voice 12: Heard it on the radio. (Multiple voices) Voice 13: I got a call from my father. Voice 14: The phone rang, it woke me up. My business partner told me to turn on the television. Voice 15: So I switched on the television. Voice 16: All channels in Italy were displaying the same thing. Voice 17: The Twin Towers. Voice 18: The Twin Towers. JB: And you move from there into that open, cavernous space. This is the so-called slurry wall. It's the original, excavated wall at the base of the World Trade Center that withstood the actual pressure from the Hudson River for a full year after the event itself. And so we thought about carrying that sense of authenticity, of presence of that moment into the actual exhibition itself. And we tell the stories of being inside the towers through that same audio collage, so you're hearing people literally talking about seeing the planes as they make their way into the building, or making their way down the stairwells. And as you make your way into the exhibition where it talks about the recovery, we actually project directly onto these moments of twisted steel all of the experiences from people who literally excavated on top of the pile itself. And so you can hear oral histories -- so people who were actually working the so-called bucket brigades as you're seeing literally the thousands of experiences from that moment. And as you leave that storytelling moment understanding about 9/11, we then turn the museum back into a moment of listening and actually talk to the individual visitors and ask them their own experiences about 9/11. And we ask them questions that are actually not really answerable, the types of questions that 9/11 itself draws forth for all of us. And so these are questions like, "How can a democracy balance freedom and security?" "How could 9/11 have happened?" "And how did the world change after 9/11?" And so these oral histories, which we've actually been capturing already for years, are then mixed together with interviews that we're doing with people like Donald Rumsfeld, Bill Clinton, Rudy Giuliani, and you mix together these different players and these different experiences, these different reflection points about 9/11. And suddenly the institution, once again, turns into a listening experience. So I'll play you just a short excerpt of a mockup that we made of a couple of these voices, but you really get a sense of the poetry of everyone's reflection on the event. (Video) Voice 1: 9/11 was not just a New York experience. Voice 2: It's something that we shared, and it's something that united us. Voice 3: And I knew when I saw that, people who were there that day who immediately went to help people known and unknown to them was something that would pull us through. Voice 4: All the outpouring of affection and emotion that came from our country was something really that will forever, ever stay with me. Voice 5: Still today I pray and think about those who lost their lives, and those who gave their lives to help others, but I'm also reminded of the fabric of this country, the love, the compassIon, the strength, and I watched a nation come together in the middle of a terrible tragedy. JB: And so as people make their way out of the museum, reflecting on the experience, reflecting on their own thoughts of it, they then move into the actual space of the memorial itself, because they've gone back up to grade, and we actually got involved in the memorial after we'd done the museum for a few years. The original designer of the memorial, Michael Arad, had this image in his mind of all the names appearing undifferentiated, almost random, really a poetic reflection on top of the nature of a terrorism event itself, but it was a huge challenge for the families, for the foundation, certainly for the first responders, and there was a negotiation that went forth and a solution was found to actually create not an order in terms of chronology, or in terms of alphabetical, but through what's called meaningful adjacency. So these are groupings of the names themselves which appear undifferentiated but actually have an order, and we, along with Jer Thorp, created an algorithm to take massive amounts of data to actually start to connect together all these different names themselves. So this is an image of the actual algorithm itself with the names scrambled for privacy, but you can see that these blocks of color are actually the four different flights, the two different towers, the first responders, and you can actually see within that different floors, and then the green lines are the interpersonal connections that were requested by the families themselves. And so when you go to the memorial, you can actually see the overarching organization inside of the individual pools themselves. You can see the way that the geography of the event is reflected inside of the memorial, and you can search for an individual name, or in this case an employer, Cantor Fitzgerald, and see the way in which all of those names, those hundreds of names, are actually organized onto the memorial itself, and use that to navigate the memorial. And more importantly, when you're actually at the site of the memorial, you can see those connections. You can see the relationships between the different names themselves. So suddenly what is this undifferentiated, anonymous group of names springs into reality as an individual life. In this case, Harry Ramos, who was the head trader at an investment bank, who stopped to aid Victor Wald on the 55th floor of the South Tower. And Ramos told Wald, according to witnesses, "I'm not going to leave you." And Wald's widow requested that they be listed next to each other. Three generations ago, we had to actually get people to go out and capture the stories for common people. Today, of course, there's an unprecedented amount of stories for all of us that are being captured for future generations. And this is our hope, that's there's poetry inside of each of our stories. Thank you very much. (Applause)
una conversación a la vez. Y la pregunta es, ¿qué te gustaría recordar si tuvieras tan solo 45 minutos con tu abuela? Lo que es interesante, en las conversaciones con el fundador, Dave Isay, en realidad siempre hablamos de esto un poco como un proyecto subversivo, porque cuando lo piensas, en realidad no es realmente acerca de las historias que se cuentan, es acerca de escuchar y es acerca de las preguntas que puedes hacer, preguntas que no tenías permiso para hacer en otra época. Voy a reproducir solo un par de pasajes rápidos del proyecto. [Jesús Meléndez habla de los últimos momentos del poeta Pedro Pietri] Jesús Meléndez: Salimos y como estábamos ascendiendo, antes de habernos estabilizado, nuestro punto de nivel inicial era de 14 km entonces antes de habernos estabilizado, Pedro empezó a dejarnos, y la belleza de esto es que creo que hay algo después de la vida. Lo puedes ver en Pedro. [Danny Perasa a su esposa Annie Perasa con quien estuvo casado 26 años] Danny Perasa: Mira, la cosa es que siempre me siento culpable cuando te digo "Te amo", y lo digo con tanta frecuencia. Lo digo para recordarte que, lleno de defectos como soy, viene desde mí, es como escuchar una canción hermosa de una vieja radio rota, y es agradable de tu parte mantener la radio en la casa. (Risas) [Michael Wolmetz con su novia Debora Brakarz] Michael Wolmetz: Este es el anillo que mi padre le dio a mi madre, y podemos dejarlo ahí. Y ahorró y lo compró y le propuso matrimonio a mi madre con él, y entonces pensé que iba a dártelo a ti para que pudiera estar con nosotros para esto también. Así que voy a compartir el micrófono contigo en este momento, Débora. ¿Dónde está el dedo derecho? Debora Brakarz: (Llorando) MW: Debora, ¿te casarías conmigo? DB: Sí. Por supuesto. Te amo. (Besos) MW: Niños, así es como su madre y yo nos casamos, en un stand en la estación Grand Central, con el anillo de mi padre. Mi abuelo fue taxista por 40 años. Recogía gente aquí todos los días. Por lo que parece apropiado. Jake Barton: Debo decir que en realidad no elegí estas muestras individuales para hacerlos llorar porque todos los hacen llorar. Todo el proyecto se basa en este acto de amor que es escuchar en sí mismo. Y el movimiento de construir una institución de un momento de conversar y escuchar tiene que ver mucho con lo que mi firma, Local Projects, está haciendo con nuestros compromisos en general. Así que somos una empresa de diseño de medios de comunicación y estamos trabajando con una amplia gama de diferentes instituciones construyendo instalaciones de medios de comunicación para museos y espacios públicos. Nuestro último trabajo es el Museo de Arte de Cleveland, para el que hemos creado un trabajo llamado Galería Uno. Y Galería Uno es un proyecto interesante porque comenzó con esta masiva expansión de $350 millones para el Museo de Arte de Cleveland y en realidad llevamos esta pieza específicamente para cultivar nuevas capacidades, nuevas audiencias, al mismo tiempo que el propio museo está creciendo. Glenn Lowry, director del MoMA, lo expresó mejor cuando dijo: "Queremos que los visitantes dejen de ser visitantes. Los visitantes son transitorios. Queremos a la gente que vive aquí, personas que tienen la propiedad". Así que lo que estamos haciendo es hacer un arreglo amplio de diferentes maneras para que la gente participe efectivamente con el material en el interior de estas galerías, por lo que aún puedes tener una experiencia tradicional de galería, pero si estás interesado, puedes participar con cualquier obra de arte individual y ver el contexto original de dónde viene, o manipular la propia obra. Entonces, por ejemplo, puedes hacer click en esta cabeza individual de león, y aquí es donde se originó, 1300 a. C. O esta pieza individual aquí, puedes ver el dormitorio real. Realmente cambia el modo en que piensas acerca de este tipo de pinturas al temple. Esta es una de mis favoritas porque se ve el propio estudio. Este es el busto de Rodin. Uno tiene la sensación de esta increíble fábrica de creatividad. Y que te hace literalmente pensar en los cientos, o miles de años de la creatividad humana y la forma en que cada obra de arte individual representa una parte de esa historia. Este es Picasso, que por supuesto representa mucho de lo que es el siglo XX. La próxima interfaz, que voy a mostrar, aprovecha la idea de este linaje de creatividad. Es un algoritmo que te permite navegar la colección vigente del museo utilizando el reconocimiento facial. Esta persona está haciendo diferentes caras, y dibujando sucesivamente diferentes objetos de la colección que se conectan con exactamente lo que está buscando. Y así te puedes imaginar que, mientras las personas se están presentando dentro del propio museo, recibes este sentido de esta conexión emocional, la forma en que nuestro rostro se conecta con los miles y decenas de miles de años. Se trata de una interfaz que realmente te permite dibujar y luego dibuja sucesivamente objetos usando las mismas formas. Así que cada vez más estamos tratando de encontrar la manera de que la gente en realidad sea un autor dentro de los museos, de que sean creativos aunque estén viendo la creatividad de otras personas y entendiéndolos Así que en este muro, el muro de las colecciones, pueden ver todas las 3000 obras de arte, todas al mismo tiempo, y pueden realizar sus propios paseos individuales por el museo, y pueden compartirlos, y alguien puede hacer un recorrido con el director del museo o una excursión con un primo. Pero todo el tiempo que hemos estado trabajando en este trabajo con Cleveland, también hemos estado trabajando en el fondo en nuestro mayor trabajo hasta la fecha, el Monumento y Museo sobre el 11-S. Comenzamos en el 2006 como parte de un equipo con Thinc Design para crear el plan maestro original para el museo, y hemos hecho todo el diseño de medios tanto para el museo y el monumento y luego la producción de medios. El monumento se inauguró en 2011, y el museo va a abrir el próximo año, en el 2014. Y como pueden ver en estas imágenes, el sitio es tan puro y casi arqueológico. Y por supuesto el evento en sí es tan reciente, en algún lugar entre la historia y los acontecimientos actuales, que fue un gran desafío imaginar cómo se sobrevive realmente hasta un espacio como este, un evento como éste, para contar esa historia. Entonces comenzamos con una nueva forma de pensar acerca de construir una institución, a través de un proyecto llamado Hagamos Historia, que lanzamos en 2009. Estimamos que un tercio del mundo vio el 11-S en vivo, un tercio del mundo escuchó sobre él durante 24 horas, con total naturalidad lo que sucedió durante este momento sin precedentes de conciencia global. Así que lanzamos esto para capturar las historias de todo el mundo, a través de video, a través de fotos, a través de la historia escrita, y así las experiencias de las personas en ese día, que era, de hecho, este enorme riesgo para la institución hacer su primer movimiento de esta plataforma abierta. Pero eso se acopló con esta cabina de historias orales, realmente lo más simple que hemos hecho, donde te encuentras a ti mismo en un mapa. Está en seis idiomas y puedes contar tu propia historia sobre lo que te pasó en ese día. Y cuando empezamos a ver las increíbles imágenes y las historias que llegaron de todo el mundo, esto es obviamente parte del tren de aterrizaje, realmente comenzamos a entender que había una increíble simetría entre el evento, entre la forma en que la gente estaba contando las historias sobre el evento, y la forma en que nosotros necesitábamos contar esa historia. Esta imagen en particular, realmente capturó nuestra atención en ese momento, porque resume ese evento. Esta es una foto del túnel Brooklyn-Battery. Hay un carro de bomberos atrapado en el tráfico, y los bomberos están corriendo 2 km y medio hasta el sitio con más de 30 kg de equipo en su espalda. Y tenemos este increíble correo electrónico que decía: "Al ver las miles de fotos en el sitio, inesperadamente encontré una foto de mi hijo. Fue un shock emocional, pero una bendición encontrar esta foto", y estaba escribiendo porque, "Me gustaría agradecer personalmente al fotógrafo por publicar la foto, ya que significa más de lo que las palabras pueden describirme para tener acceso a lo que es probablemente la última foto tomada de mi hijo". Y la verdad es que nos hace reconocer lo que esta institución necesitaba hacer para contar realmente la historia. No podemos tener solo un historiador o un curador que narre objetivamente en tercera persona acerca de un evento así, cuando existen los testigos de la historia que van a hacer su camino a través del museo en sí. Entonces comenzamos a imaginar el museo, junto con el equipo creativo del museo y los curadores, pensando en cómo la primera voz que se oye dentro del museo sería en realidad la de otros visitantes. Y por eso hemos creado esta idea de una galería abierta que llamamos Recordamos. Voy a reproducirles una parte de una maqueta de la misma, pero les dará una idea de lo que se siente al entrar en ese momento en el tiempo y ser transportado hacia atrás en la historia. (Video) Voz 1: Estaba en Honolulu, Hawái. Voz 2: Estaba en El Cairo, Egipto. Voz 3: Al sur de los Campos Elíseos, en París. Voz 4: En la universidad, en U.C. Berkeley. Voz 5: Estaba en Times Square. Voz 6: São Paulo, Brasil. (Voces múltiples) Voz 7: Fue probablemente alrededor de las 11 de la noche. Voz 8: Estaba conduciendo al trabajo a la hora local 5:45 de la mañana. Voz 9: En realidad estábamos en una reunión cuando alguien irrumpió y dijo: "Oh, Dios mío, un avión se ha estrellado contra el World Trade Center". Voz 10: Tratando de conseguir desesperadamente un radio. Voz 11: Cuando lo escuché por la radio... Voz 12: Lo escuché en la radio. (Voces múltiples) Voz 13: Recibí una llamada de mi padre. Voz 14: El teléfono sonó, me despertó. Mi compañero de trabajo me dijo que encendiera la televisión. Voz 15: Así que encendí la televisión. Voz 16: Todos los canales en Italia mostraban lo mismo. Voz 17: Las Torres Gemelas. Voz 18: Las Torres Gemelas. JB: Y te mueves a partir de ahí a ese cavernoso espacio abierto. Este es el llamado muro pantalla. Es la pared excavada en la base original del World Trade Center que resistió la presión del río Hudson durante un año completo después del evento. Entonces pensamos en llevar esa sensación de autenticidad, de la presencia de ese momento en la exposición en sí. Y contamos las historias de estar dentro de las torres a través de ese mismo collage de audio, lo que están escuchando, son literalmente personas hablando sobre ver a los aviones estrellándose en el edificio, o bajando por las escaleras. Y conforme haces el camino en la exposición donde se habla de la recuperación, realmente proyectamos directamente en esos momentos de acero trenzado, todas las experiencias de la gente que literalmente escarbaban en la parte superior de la pila. Y para que puedan escuchar historias orales, las personas que estaban realmente trabajando en las llamadas brigadas de cubo mientras están viendo, literalmente, miles de experiencias de ese momento. Y al salir de ese momento de narración comprendiendo sobre el 11-S, regresamos al museo de nuevo a un momento de escucha y a hablar con los visitantes individuales y pedirles sus propias experiencias sobre el 11-S. Y les hacemos preguntas que en realidad no son realmente contestables, los tipos de preguntas que el 11-S en sí atrae sucesivamente para todos nosotros. Y así, se trata de cuestiones como, "¿Cómo puede la democracia balancear la libertad y la seguridad?" "¿Cómo puede haber sucedido el 11-S?" "¿Y cómo cambió el mundo después del 11-S?" Y así estas historias orales, que hemos estado capturando ya desde hace años, se mezclan luego junto con entrevistas que estamos haciendo con gente como Donald Rumsfeld, Bill Clinton, Rudy Giuliani, y se mezclan juntos estos diferentes actores y estas experiencias diferentes, estos diferentes puntos de reflexión sobre el 11-S. Y de pronto la institución, una vez más, se convierte en una experiencia de sonido. Así que Ies reproduciré un breve extracto de una maqueta que hicimos de un par de estas voces, pero realmente tendrán una sensación de la poesía de la reflexión de todos en el evento. (Video) Voz 1: El 11-S no fue solo una experiencia de Nueva York. Voz 2: Es algo que compartimos, y es algo que nos unía. Voz 3: Y supe cuando vi que, las personas que estaban allí ese día de inmediato fueron a ayudar a la gente conocida y desconocida para ellos fue algo que nos haría salir adelante. Voz 4: Toda la efusión de afecto y emoción que venía de nuestro país era algo realmente que para siempre se quedará conmigo. Voz 5: Todavía hoy rezo y pienso en los que perdieron la vida, y aquellos que dieron su vida por salvar a otros, pero también me recuerda a la estructura de este país, el amor, la compasión, la fuerza, y vi a una nación unida en el medio de una terrible tragedia. JB: Y mientras la gente sale del museo, reflexionando sobre la experiencia, reflexionando sobre sus propios pensamientos sobre la misma, se mueven en el espacio actual de la propia memoria, porque han regresado, y de hecho nos involucramos en el monumento después de haber hecho el museo durante unos años. El diseñador original del monumento, Michael Arad, tenía esta imagen en su mente de todos los nombres que aparecen indiferenciados, casi al azar, realmente una reflexión poética sobre la naturaleza de un evento terrorista, pero fue un gran desafío para las familias, para la fundación, sin duda para los primeros en responder, y había una negociación que salió y se encontró una solución para no crear en realidad un orden en términos cronológicos, o en términos alfabéticos, sino a través de lo que se llama adyacencia significativa. Así que estos son los grupos de los nombres propios que aparecen indiferenciados pero en realidad tienen un orden, y nosotros, junto con Jer Thorp, creamos un algoritmo para tomar grandes cantidades de datos para realmente empezar a conectar entre sí todos estos nombres. Así que esta es una imagen del algoritmo con los nombres por privacidad codificados, pero se puede ver que estos bloques de color son en realidad los cuatro vuelos diferentes, las dos diferentes torres, los primeros en actuar, y en realidad se puede ver entre los diferentes pisos, y luego las líneas verdes son las conexiones interpersonales que fueron solicitadas por las propias familias. Así que cuando van al monumento, pueden ver realmente la organización global en el interior de las propias piscinas individuales. Pueden ver la forma en que la geografía del evento se refleja en el interior del monumento, y pueden buscar un nombre individual, o en este caso un empleador, Cantor Fitzgerald, y ver la manera en que todos esos nombres, los cientos de nombres, en realidad están organizados en el monumento en sí, y usar eso para navegarlo. Y lo más importante, cuando en realidad están en el sitio del monumento, se puede ver las conexiones. Pueden ver las relaciones entre los diferentes nombres propios. Así que de repente este indiferenciado, anónimo grupo de nombres se convierten en realidad como una vida individual. En este caso, Harry Ramos, quien era el jefe de operaciones de un banco de inversión, que se detuvo a ayudar a Victor Wald en el piso 55 de la Torre Sur. Y Ramos le dijo a Wald, según testigos, "No te voy a dejar". Y la viuda de Wald solicitó que sean listados uno al lado del otro. Hace tres generaciones, tuvimos que conseguir realmente que la gente saliera y capturar las historias de personas comunes. Hoy, por supuesto, hay una cantidad sin precedentes de historias para todos nosotros que están siendo capturadas para las generaciones futuras. Y esta es nuestra esperanza, esa es la poesía que hay en el interior de cada una de nuestras historias. Muchas gracias. (Aplausos)